[Music]
the most popular doll of all time is
finally getting her big screen debut
she's an icon a legend a cultural
lightning rod and an 11 and a half inch
piece of plastic who's represented and
projected our biggest aspirations and
flaws for more than 60 years
her movie debut marks a big bet by
Mattel hi Barbie
again which hopes to turn Legacy Brands
like Barbie Hot Wheels and Rock'em
sock'em into Blockbuster franchises
think Marvel if they're lucky
with so much riding on her Tiny But
Mighty shoulders I'm stepping into
Barbie land to find out more about how
her makers are inventing her next ACT
[Music]
hello Hi how are you good to see you so
much for having us it's great to have
you this place is amazing it's fun right
yeah I'm like a kid in a toy store I
know that's how we all feel every day
when we come to work
[Music]
did you spend a lot of time on the set
yeah actually quite a bit that must have
been fun in London and some in Los
Angeles yes
I hear you've been the main driver
behind this strategy to use this
incredible and iconic IP and turn it
into movies and films and now you've got
dozens of projects in the works why do
you think this is the golden ticket the
opportunity that I saw when I joined the
company was to continue to grow the toy
business but turn Mattel from what it
used to be more of a toy Manufacturing
Company into an IP company that manages
franchises
for decades Barbie dominated kid wish
lists across the globe but more recently
all toy makers have been battling screen
time for playtime on top of supply chain
issues and Rising costs in 2014 Mattel
sales started to lag and then the Barbie
maker lost a coveted Disney Princesses
deal to Hasbro while Hasbro and Lego
managed to transform top toys into box
office hits Mattel's long-awaited Barbie
movie languished
but Fortune started to turn when Mattel
changed its business plan of attack one
Disney princess's back and convinced
Hollywood heavyweights to take a swing
at the Barbie verse the Barbie movie was
kind of in development hell wasn't it
how did you pull it out of that our
approach was different when we started
this journey the underlying objective
was to create quality content quality
experience and make a movie that people
would want to watch
cries wasn't interested in making
glorified toy ads so he brought in a
producer with big screen chops you
produce Dallas Buyers Club which was
nominated for an Oscar for Best Picture
what convinced you to come in house and
make movies for Mattel the bench of the
amazing IP that Mattel has I mean the
hundreds and hundreds of Brands owning
Fisher Price and American Girl and eight
ball and Hot Wheels and Barbie and Jack
in the Box it just the list went on when
I really you know looked deeply into it
I thought my God I grew up on so many of
these Brands I have two children they
played with Barbie they played with
American girl and you know we have so
much going on in the world right now I
mean it's just a very kind of messy
crazy time I think for everybody and I
thought wow what better place to then to
work at a toy company you're making
things that actually bring smiles to
Children's faces that actually inspire
Wonder and Imagination and just unlock
incredible things for children and and
for adults and the Nostalgia that I had
for all of these toys Barbie has a
complicated history she is a cultural
icon and a flash Point what's the goal
with the new Barbie movie everybody has
a relationship with Barbie she's been
around for so many decades and everybody
knows who Barbie is she's probably the
most famous woman in the world she's
been to the Moon she's been president
she's done all of these things that you
know women aspire to be and I think that
you know in hiring somebody like Greta
Gerwig who I think is a brilliant
filmmaker but she has a singular vision
and an authentic voice as a filmmaker
bringing somebody like that that has
just kind of a different perspective
that is outside of the box that's going
to do something differently to something
like Barbie I feel like that's when sort
of greatness occurs this is Barbie's
first theatrical release in her 60 plus
year history why was now the right time
and not 10 years ago or 20 years ago
it's interesting that of all the movies
at Mattel films since we started on this
journey four and a half years ago that
this is the first movie
you would think in a lot of ways like
that's a lot to live up to because it is
an open-ended conversation she is an
open-ended conversation like what is
that movie Greta had sort of this idea
and I remember we met with her and she
she said I have this idea of a high heel
and a Birkenstock and that was sort of
her like leaping off point of like what
this movie should be and I thought God
that's kind of brilliant I know you
partnered with Warner Brothers on this
how involved was Mattel in the script
like what were some things that were
important to you or important to Mattel
that you saw in the script that maybe
you wanted to change or that evolved
there's a responsibility to the brand
and there's a sensitivity about doing
you can't push things too far or what
are mom's gonna think or what are girls
gonna think and who is this for and what
are we making it and is this the right
conversation to have or what's
appropriate what's not appropriate what
is the no-fly zone you know what's in
the no-fly zone I'm so curious well
language
um you know certain themes that felt
like you know they didn't belong in the
movie
um but I think that we weren't afraid of
that I think if you're not doing
something that's sort of like scares you
a little you're not gonna make something
great
Barbie still drives roughly one-third of
Mattel's five billion dollar Revenue she
sparked fashion trends video games and
world-class art
but before she became the billion dollar
Breadwinner for Mattel she was just a
prototype with a very familiar Silicon
Valley style beginning
hey there hi so good to meet you thank
you for having us I'm admiring the
amazing artwork this is Donald Batchelor
a incredibly well-known pop artist but
throughout the building you'll see a lot
of incredible art inspired by of course
Barbie
Warhol downstairs of course it's one of
our prized pieces and this is a picture
of the painting that Jean-Michel
Basquiat did that incorporates the
Mattel logo in his work which of course
is such a symbol of pop culture and the
art at the time where's the real
Basquiat yeah well that's that's a
secret conversation oh okay
this actually is a really important part
of our history and uh symbolic in many
ways it is the original garage where
Mattel was founded and as you can see
above this little very discreet door was
this name called Mattel Creations really
just by the name of the company at that
time Creations what's a Creations
company I mean behind that door
essentially the creative spirit and
entrepreneurial energy and risk taking
and designers and Engineers who are
creating the future play so just like
every other startup just like every
other great startup exactly so Barbie
came out in 1959 the garage opened in
1945 yeah what happened between 1945 and
1950 a lot of work behind the garage
okay a lot a lot of hits some misses But
ultimately the founders were really
engineers and designers who were the
founders Ruth and Elliot were the
married couple Ruth and Elliott Handler
then there was another founder who we
talk about as well Harold Matt Mason now
if you kind of think through it Harold
Matt Mason and Ruth and Elliott when you
combine matte with Elliot you got Mattel
all right the missing piece of that name
is actually Ruth they wrote the woman
out of the story at that time back in
the 1940s really women were at a very
very different position in the context
of business and ownership and and
actually even at that time Ruth couldn't
even write a check which today we think
is is just unimaginable but back then it
was really the way that women were
living in the context of our society and
so today everywhere you go and
everywhere we talk about we celebrate
Ruth we celebrate her impact on the
company she is the founder of Barbie and
also really the entrepreneur who helped
Drive metal to the heights that we enjoy
today
Ruth Handler got the spark after seeing
her daughter play with paper dolls doing
what kids would do for generations to
come make up stories and imagine their
adult selves on a family trip to
Switzerland with her kids Barbara and
Ken yes that Barbie and Ken Ruth saw a
window display featuring a billed Lily
doll this wasn't for kids she was a
blonde busty figure passed around as a
gag gift at Bachelor parties
from that concept she created the first
Barbie prototype and eventually had a
hit on her hands
Barbie helped turn Mattel into the
imagination Factory it is today and
planted the seeds for an enduring
challenge marketing a doll with high
beauty standards
now we really think of what we have
today which is the design center as just
a bigger garage okay and actually you
could see it from my office we're gonna
be heading over there if you could see
that building right there with the red
angle and we call it just a bigger
garage okay I can't wait to see it yeah
fun
all right
[Music]
[Applause]
welcome to the big garage this is the
design center hey you can see Graphics
from the 60s 70s 80s 90s through today
you can find your favorite toy if you
will from a decade past our job here is
to certainly leave it better than we
found it and create the next generation
of leadership to take it on to the next
level this is Iconic fun I mean come on
the famous elevator right yeah so this
is a really fun part of the design
center and celebration of of a part of
Barbie's dream house next to it you see
this unbelievably cool Hot Wheels track
system we've got to drop some can we
actually drop cars down of course
that's Hot Wheels challenge your spirit
our objective is going to be to get it
in one of those all right crates we'll
see how we do
well I have three sons so I'm pretty
good challenge accepted I'm just gonna
talk a little smack all right let's go
one two three
[Music]
okay so you're pretty good at this I
live here next time
oh
what you start to really understand is
you sort of look at where Mattel was and
the toys that we were creating in
connection to what was happening in
culture is how much toys are a canvas
for pop cultural conversation can we go
to 1959 we can we can that's right here
in 1959 and there she is in all her
glory the first Barbie was a fashion
model right the first Barbie was a
fashion model that's right and then she
expanded her into many many different
careers and ultimately today with
thousands of careers represented and
today is the most diverse and inclusive
doll brand in the world
she used to help the book that said
don't eat there was another a teen
Barbie I think that said math class is
tough yikes yeah yeah there were there
were lots of uh parts of our history
that ultimately in the moment that they
were created probably with the right
intent either were misinterpreted or
ultimately you know became part of a
cultural conversation that had more
negativity associated with it and so
while there's been controversy and
cultural conversations around it our job
has been to keep the brand relevant and
current in the context of culture
so now we're entering the Barbie section
of the design center and of course
you'll see everything Barbie and as you
pass through all of these These are face
painters in there oh wow wow yeah you
get to uh to really see some of the
amazing artists and the Arts themselves
this is kind of spooky great yeah this
is where you kind of see all of the
Barbie Scopes imagine all these
different heads and sculpts and
hairstyles and face painters and all
these different ways to express the
brand especially in more recent years
you started doing consumer surveys and
talking to kids about Barbie what were
they telling you
well we've gone through you know an
evolution of the brand in back in
2014 it was really marked a pivotal
moment for us where the brand was not
doing well in the marketplace the
feedback that we were getting from
consumers was she just didn't seem
relevant
indeed 2014 marked the third consecutive
year of falling sales for Barbie the
cultural conversation was shifting
beneath them and parents were giving
feedback by closing their pocketbooks
while Mattel touted Barbie as a strong
woman who could have any job she wanted
consumers were embracing body positivity
and inclusivity and saw a
picture-perfect Barbie as out of date
and out of touch forcing Mattel back to
the drawing board
we were getting some really bad playback
from parents and the biggest flag that
we heard when we did some research was
moms in particular didn't feel good
about giving Barbie as a birthday gift
that's a sign of sort of their personal
brand and social currency that Barbie
was missing they didn't see her as a
role model they saw her as too perfect
and then of course her body had always
been a topic so we knew we needed to
address that too and that's exactly what
the team did we Diversified the brand we
introduced 24 different skin tones
representing ethnicities around the
world that girls see we changed her body
and introduced nine different shapes
tall petite curvy and Etc we kept the
original but we expanded for Choice do
you think Mattel should have changed
faster should Barbie have changed faster
in your view look I think the business
would have suggested the Barbie should
have changed faster for sure and we had
gone through a pit to understand the
Dynamics of how to get out of that that
has led us to today's Barbie which is
unbelievably culturally relevant is on
the cusp of this theatrical film that we
couldn't be more proud of okay
Barbie's history is so rich
leave all of that into a film so we had
so much fun working with the filmmakers
to bring these amazing characters to
life so of course you see
Margo Barbie we call her the OG she's
wearing key looks from key scenes in the
films Barbie has a long history with the
Corvette from GM and so we had to create
this this is a really popular vehicle in
the movie
and then Ken of course is just Ken did
you bring your rollerblades
I literally go nowhere without them and
of course you didn't know who it was
just look at his little undies
we invited them in early on and gave
them a full brand immersion we went
through the archives we shared the
fashion history of Barbie we shared the
evolution of the Barbie and her careers
all the fun stories some of the mishaps
as well along the way like what mishaps
fun dolls that sort of didn't hit the
mark at a moment in time one was fashion
earring Ken
um you know just just fun dolls that
weren't big commercial successes but
have fandom with collectors from decades
ago and so they got really close to all
those details so again lots of cues from
some of the most popular looks
throughout the decades
now we're going to enter probably you
know one of the most important parts of
the dial design and development process
which is of course Barbie's hair ah yes
come on yeah it sounds important part of
the play pattern
everything starts with a sketch and it
starts with the designer's vision and
then we have an incredible group of hair
designers and face designers that bring
the designer's vision to life in 3D what
were the challenges that you faced
trying to make her more diverse and
experiment with these materials that
you've been we're using for decades but
then had to change we are always looking
at sort of what representation means and
how important that is and sort of seeing
who do we serve currently how can we
serve more people better and what does
that mean it's not always just a simple
thing of a visual thing about Aesthetics
it's about differently abled communities
it's about representation in its
broadest form because we know we're not
done right it's not like you can just
kind of rest on our florals
no Laurel resting here I'm into this one
right here I mean like I don't think I
couldn't tell this off yeah
yeah
she looks pretty badass the range as
well as like everything this I think was
actually done for a collector doll
whereas like a younger audience younger
kids it's about brushing the hair
styling the hair playing with it so
these really long hairstyles like this
incredible crimped style this would have
been so fun to brush yeah I mean I did a
lot of brushes just like I did some
cutting too I mean how do you we know
that I love it I love it cut away yeah
like I think it's the whole thing of
giving permission that's the play the
play aspect is like not limiting what
that means and kids Define it themselves
cutting the hair is a big part of it
because it's this thing of like you see
it happen in real life and you're like
that seems like a good idea I'm gonna do
that tomorrow and the next thing you
know is tears and a horrible hairstyle
and your Barbie has something yeah I bet
but that's actually the best part of
Barbie right we put the doll in the box
but she comes to life when she gets in
the hands of a kid and that's the beauty
that's the magic goes the Barbie brand
[Music]
when kids play with Barbie they use
their imagination they put her in scenes
they dress her up
in a way they decide who they want
Barbie to be how did you decide who you
wanted Barbie to be in this film when
you look at Margot she's incredibly you
know beautiful and she sort of looks
like probably the traditional Barbie she
was very very passionate about about
telling the story of Barbie and doing
something different and kind of
unexpected and then it went from there
why cast Margot Robbie if you are trying
to involve the brand or who Barbie can
be there are many Ken's and there are
many Barbies and I think that you know
everybody can find somebody that they
identify with that she's just one Barbie
and she happens to be the Barbie that we
go on the journey with I think that
Barbie can be a friend can be a sounding
board can be a you know a place where
kids can imagine and dream and you know
just just a place to explore that their
their emotions and their Wonder for the
world or their aspiration of who they
want to be is women and that you could
be anything I mean the diversity of
these dolls of all of the dolls that
they put out it's so inspiring Mattel
has so many iconic Brands there's Barbie
there's Hot Wheels there's Fisher Price
an American Girl and Thomas the Train
and Masters of the Universe
what are your plans to leverage the rest
of this IP into a new kind of
entertainment well we've announced 14
but we have almost 40 that we're
developing can Hot Wheels take on Fast
and Furious what do you think so
what's that one gonna look like sorry
Ben
it's going to be great we're developing
it with JJ Abrams it's going to be
fantastic it's going to be big it's
going to have a strong point of view and
it's yeah it's going to be a big
franchise we want our movies to have
integrity and authenticity but we also
want them to be amazing Stories we don't
need to make movies to sell toys
you aren't projecting a bump in sales
after the movie why not it's not just
about this quarter or the year it's
really a long-term franchise management
strategy to create more engaging
experiences so it's not just about the
money because I think folks would say
well if it's not about the money why
bother
it is not just about the money of course
we are a commercial Enterprise and as
such we're looking to grow our business
increase profitability and all the
things that we are here to achieve you
spend a lot of time on the set it sounds
like
you care a lot about this movie it's
kind of like your baby
finish this sentence the new Barbie
movie will be a success if
it's an event and an event not just for
Mattel we believe it will be a a
cultural event this has been our North
Star how do we support that purpose and
continue to evolve the brand with so
many more opportunities when it comes to
Bobby the question is how high is high
in terms of where Barbie can grow what
can Barbie do with all this promise of
Hollywood size Productions and a fresh
content strategy I wondered about the
doll at the center of it all was she
still worth playing with on her own
anymore is she enough for kids today or
will emerging technology influence her
future once again
some people love technology and what it
represents in kids lives and some people
fear it and ultimately have a lot of
caution around it we take unbelievable
caution and protection and everything
that we do including technology You
released an AI -powered Barbie a few
years back hello Barbie yeah sometimes
we get it really right and sometimes
we're ahead of ourselves I would say
hello Barbie was probably ahead of its
time yeah there was a lot of backlash I
mean what was the response we've had a
few of those where we swung early and
probably on the Forefront of the future
but it doesn't necessarily mean that
we're not going to take another swing
soon so do you see a doll that can talk
to kids in the future
we all know the next wave is coming the
question of how we apply Barbie's
purpose design-led insights into an
extension of what that means in people's
lives is obviously something that we
will eventually get to and now you're
competing with iPads and
technology everywhere how does screen
time beat playtime we don't think we
compete with screen time we can
integrate Barbie into screen time
appropriately we also see a trend
reflecting back to the values of
traditional play screen time and
technology is an important part of our
Lives an important part of development
but I think that there's also a trend
right now that we're seeing with parents
who are returning back to seeing their
kids and playing with their kids right
on the floor experiencing that tactile
play pattern recognizing that the
conversation associated with objects can
reveal incredible personality traits and
Child Development aspects from cognitive
social emotional and physical
development we love traditional play but
we think the digital dialogue is only
expanding the playground
[Music]
foreign